- Okay.
Thank you all for being here,
and thanks for your patience as we get set up.
We're gonna be doing a little bit
of musical laptops this morning,
but I think we've got all the technology pieces settled,
so it's great to see so many of you here for this.
We've got two great panelists with us here today,
so I'll do full introductions in a minute.
But Juliet Rothenberg, who's the product director
of Earth & Resilience AI at Google,
and Gaurav Khanna, AI executive at Cisco Systems.
And then I'm Carla Grande.
I am at
the California Community College Chancellor's Office.
I'm the chancellor's senior advisor on climate
and the lead climate fellow.
And so this is
an exciting panel,
like, I'm really excited to hear from them.
But one of the conversations
that we have a lot within the chancellor's office,
and as we're talking to colleges
about the climate change work
and the AI work
is how do you reconcile those two things?
So this comes up a lot with students,
it comes up a lot with our climate team,
it's come up with our board of governors asking us, like,
"How can you have these two areas of focus
that seem like they're in competition with each other?"
And so just to give you a little bit,
you've heard a lot about the AI work
that we're doing at the chancellor's office,
and we've heard a lot of exciting opportunities
that AI provides.
But I wanna just share a little bit about the climate work
that we're doing before I turn it over.
So, under Vision 2030,
the 116 California Community Colleges
have been asked to lead the way in climate action.
And so trying to take a holistic approach to that,
looking at opportunities for community engagement,
workforce development, facilities and operations,
so minimizing our greenhouse gas emissions from our campuses
and also integrating climate action into the curriculum.
So the two speakers
who we're gonna hear from today
are gonna talk with us
about kind of two sides of that,
the climate AI paradox,
so both potential solutions
that AI can bring to climate challenges
and also some
of the energy consumption issues that we're dealing with.
And I think the speaker this morning
really set us up nicely for that.
So they're gonna share a little bit about their work,
and then I've got some questions for them,
but I also want to make sure that we save time
for audience questions.
So please, as they're talking,
think about what questions you have,
because I will give you all an opportunity
to ask questions as we go.
So without further ado,
I will start with Juliet.
So Juliet is a product director
of Earth & Resilience AI at Google,
where her teams lead over 20 projects
focused on applying AI to enable a more resilient earth.
Her team's work was the sole basis
for Google being awarded Fast Company's
World Changing Company of the Year in 2024.
Juliet has focused on energy, transportation,
and resilience for the past 20 years
and has worked in AI at Alphabet for the past eight.
Juliet previously led the enterprise PM team at DeepMind
across industrial, efficiency, renewables,
language, and document AI.
Before DeepMind, Juliet had
the in-car and app experiences at Waymo,
and she led the cross-company launch
of Waymo's user-facing service.
So I am going to start off with Juliet
and ask her,
please share with us, in your perspective,
AI's potential for solving
some of these environmental issues
and helping to save our planet.
- Thank you very much, Carla,
and thank you everyone for being here.
It's an honor for me to be here at a personal level as well.
My mom has spent 20 years working
in the community college industry,
and it's something that means a ton to me
to be able to give back in this way.
So, sorry, sometimes I get sentimental
when I think about where I've come from
and where I get to be now.
But let's talk about what we get to do, right?
And what can we do with AI and solutions in this space?
We're lucky to have a whole variety of different areas.
And Carla, when you asked me to speak initially,
I thought I can give an overview of a number of them
and then we can dig into any
that anyone has questions around.
But I just wanna give a flavor of the type of problems
that AI can solve.
So we'll start out with talking about solutions
in transportation and energy.
How many of you like stop-and-go traffic?
Nobody, right? (laughs)
Turns out the climate doesn't like
stop-and-go traffic either.
Pollution at intersections is 29 times higher
than on open roads,
and over half of that comes from vehicles
accelerating after they stop.
And so what our Project Greenlight team has been doing
is using Google Maps driving trends together with AI
to help traffic engineers make small changes
to traffic lights,
think, take a few seconds off of the quote unquote,
"green time" from this direction
and give a few more seconds to this direction,
or coordinate this one traffic light
with another traffic light.
And what we've seen is that traffic engineers
are able to change an intersection in a matter of minutes,
and we've seen up to 30% reduction
in stop-and-go traffic, up to 10% reduction in emissions.
We're now live in over 20 cities around the world,
including Boston, my hometown of Seattle,
Rio de Janeiro, Jakarta, Indonesia, Bangalore,
a whole variety of cities
where we're seeing this capability generalize
and expand really quickly.
I've been to a number
of different traffic engineering centers around the world.
They're really fun to visit, by the way.
They have a lot of screens up everywhere.
And traffic engineers try to get
to every traffic light in their city every five years
to retime it,
because their cities and their worlds are changing.
You ask them whether they do that or not,
and they say, "No, of course I don't.
I don't have time.
I can't get to all of these intersections."
And so AI is really able to help accelerate their ability
to get their work done to help us move
in a more sustainable way around cities.
And I think that this really shows the power of AI, right?
I mean, I'm sure we've all noticed
just how quickly AI has shifted,
and with the beauty of AI's speed and scale
is that you can then get speed and scale
across other industries and other infrastructure
where we need that for sustainability solutions.
And so Greenlight is one example of that.
How many of you're familiar with airplane contrails?
Has anybody heard of this
as a sustainability and a climate solution?
Yes, okay, that makes me very happy to hear,
because previously, prior to our team working on this,
basically no one would've raised
their hand in a room like this.
And now we have a few,
so I hope after this, all of you will be able
to raise your hand with what contrails are.
But they're those little wispy clouds behind planes.
They're called a contrail.
And the thing that's interesting about contrails
is they're responsible for over 1/3
of aviation's warming impact.
Usually you think of fuel, right?
But contrails are actually really significantly warming.
They come from cirrus clouds.
If any of you are outdoorsy
and you like to camp,
you know that cloudy nights are warmer than cool nights,
or clear nights.
The way that contrails work is very similar.
They trap heat into the Earth's atmosphere at night.
And we've used AI to predict where contrails will form
and had pilots in live flights
adjust the altitude of their flight
just like they do for turbulence,
like you've probably seen,
and they've reduced contrails by over 50%.
We've done this with a number of flights
with American Airlines.
We're now working with EU air traffic control actually,
where over a significant amount of airspace in Europe,
they're actually automatically adjusting
the altitude of flights.
And what's so exciting about this
is for those of you who follow sustainable aviation, right,
the other solutions in sustainability and aviation
look like electric planes,
hydrogen planes, biofuels.
We need those solutions too.
But those solutions are gonna take decades to scale.
And the VP of sustainability
for American Airlines went on national TV
and said that this is something that can scale
across the industry in two to five years.
And so that's the power that you can bring of AI,
is to really transform industries
at a speed and scale that we have not seen
through other solutions to date.
And we desperately need this speed, right?
I think none of us in this room probably need
to be convinced that we have to act very quickly
from a sustainability standpoint.
Oh, this is just a picture of how it works.
These are contrails on the left,
you can see contrail from the ground
in a photo.
On the right, you can see them in satellite imagery.
And so we trained an AI model to use satellite imagery
to be able to detect contrails.
And then we used AI as well,
this model coupled with weather data
to predict where contrails will form.
And so that formed the basis of our work.
I drove here today and was a few minutes late.
Thank you for your patience.
Who else drove here today?
Yes?
Who used Google Maps?
Yeah?
Did you notice the green leaf
in Google Maps when you were driving?
Did you know before what it was?
Yeah, a couple dots. Great.
This is a great room.
So it's our fuel-efficient routing feature.
So we share through Google Maps
the most fuel-efficient route
in cases where it isn't already the fastest,
where the time is, you know, maybe just a little bit longer,
30 seconds longer,
a couple of minutes longer, something like that.
And we've seen that this has been able
to scale up really beautifully globally.
So we're now sharing this
with all Google Maps users around the world.
You can go into settings and you can turn it off
if you like, but the majority of users really appreciate it.
And we see that we're able to save megatons of CO2
through this work each year.
And so it's really able to drive a significant impact.
Another example, many of you
may have solar.
Solars are a great solution in California,
but if you have solar,
I imagine many of you
like the sustainability benefits of it,
but most people decide to go solar based on cost.
And so Google is an information company
and we look to say, "Great, can we provide information
so that people can make a well-rounded decision?"
And we've used AI models
to help model out what the cost savings
can be for hundreds of millions
of buildings worldwide if they go solar.
And what we've seen
is that this significantly reduces the time
for a someone who's selling solar
to convert someone into a purchaser.
And it reduces their cost of customer acquisition.
So we can actually make it cheaper for people to go solar
by providing better information in this way.
This is used by a very large percentage
of solar installers in the U.S.
and increasingly around the world
to help build more sustainable solutions.
So, that's kind of on the sustainability side.
Let's talk a bit more about resilience,
because unfortunately, I'm sure many of you
have been affected by the climate events
that we're already seeing.
If you lived in the Bay Area in 2020,
I'm sure you remember when the skies
were red from wildfires,
and we're seeing an increasing number of disasters strike.
This has actually been a pretty good year, surprisingly,
but of course, you know, we had
the flash floods in Texas, right?
And we had the fires in LA.
Even with that,
it's actually been a better than average year.
My team manages the crisis events
that get sent out to Google users.
We send out millions of those every day.
And so we monitor around the world disasters
and are able to help provide information
to people who are in harm's way.
And we use AI models
as a key part of providing this information.
And part of this is because people turn to Google
in times of crisis, right?
If there's a disaster, what should I do?
Let me check the internet, let me see what's going on.
And so this has been a natural role
that Google has been playing.
One of the things that we do,
wildfires obviously strike close to home,
I was a half mile away from the CCU wildfires
and so we were evacuated.
And wildfire boundaries are a feature
that we've launched since,
which have been extraordinarily helpful,
live in 27 countries
where we show wildfire boundaries straight on Google Maps.
So in addition to being able
to get your great boundaries from Watch Duty,
which is a google.org grantee, by the way,
we're very supportive of their work,
as well as being able to get them from Cal Fire maps.
You can also see boundaries
right on Google Maps using AI and satellite imagery.
Now, one of the things you might have noticed,
and I noticed this very much when we were evacuated,
is that current satellite data's
not very good when it comes to wildfires.
So I was getting updates, if the fire crossed the road,
our community would've burned.
Fortunately, it didn't.
But we were checking satellite inventory constantly,
trying to refresh, saying, "Has the fire crossed the road?
Is our community safe?"
And we got updates twice a day,
because that's about how often
you can see with that level of granularity.
And so our team recently launched the first satellite
and a constellation of satellites
designed to provide much better data
for these types of scenarios,
being able to detect a swimming pool-sized wildfire
anywhere on Earth within 20 minutes,
compared to two to three acres today.
So really, really changing up the game using AI
to process this massive amount of imagery
to be able to provide fast wildfire detection.
We need 52 satellites for this constellation to succeed.
So far we have one,
so it's gonna be a journey,
but every journey starts somewhere, right?
And we're taking the first step on this
in partnership with a nonprofit, the Earth Fire Alliance.
If you know people who would like to contribute
to making this mission possible, we absolutely welcome that.
But it's something that we are very committed to
and really excited to drive more of.
Floods are another disaster that, you know,
less relevant for California,
but relevant of course
for many other places around the world.
And we have a global team.
And actually, the work for this flood forecasting
started out of one of our teams in the Middle East.
That's an AI research team.
Floods are one of the most deadly disasters
around the world,
affecting a tremendous number of people every year.
And the other piece that we saw is that flood forecasting
and good flood forecasts correlate with GDP.
So basically, richer countries have better flood forecasts
and poorer, more vulnerable countries
have worse flood forecasts.
And our team said, "Can we use an AI model to be able
to provide more globally equitable flood forecasts
around the world
so that we could really help with communities who need?"
And the answer was yes.
We published this work in "Nature,"
and we're able to provide
European-quality flood forecasts for Africa.
We also were able to extend the lead time of floods
up to seven days in advance using AI.
So instead of saying, "Hey, the flood is here now,"
with that same level of accuracy, we could say,
"Hey, the flood will be here in seven days,"
providing significantly time,
for those of you who have lived in flood zones, you know,
sandbags for example are one key solution,
or protecting livestock and animals
or moving your goods onto the second floor.
There are a whole variety of solutions
that people can take if they have days notice ahead.
And so this is something that we provide.
These forecasts are freely available via Google Flood Hub
for over a hundred countries
covering locations where over 700 million people live.
So this has been something
that's been a big commitment of our team,
and it is really important
to us from a global equity standpoint.
Our work in cyclones also has gotten
significant press this summer,
and we've already started to see cyclones hit.
We recently released
together between Google Research and Google DeepMind
a breakthrough, experimental cyclones models
that can predict both the track
and the intensity of cyclones up to 15 days in advance.
This is now being tested this season
by the National Hurricane Center,
as well as some of our partners in Japan
for predicting hurricanes.
And this recently, sorry for the ugly slide here,
but I screenshotted this from one of the former leads
of the National Hurricane Center for hurricane forecasting,
and Hurricane Aaron at the time this came out
was the strongest storm of the year so far.
This is just from a few weeks ago.
Lower is better on these graphs.
These graphs are showing error,
and the model that we came out with is the red line.
And so we're seeing more accurate predictions
for both track and intensity of hurricanes using AI,
really driving a significant breakthrough
in a way that has not been seen in the past.
One other solution here is extreme heat.
So we've been working with the city of Miami,
the city of Phoenix,
15 other cities around the world
for being able to help them to understand
what policy solutions they can take for reducing heat.
You might be familiar with cool roofs,
when you paint your roof,
white people are familiar with that, yeah?
So that's one solution for extreme heat.
And if you can give cities the ability to understand,
"What is my cool roof coverage at a city level?"
That allows 'em to understand
what policy tools they have in mind.
Also, tree canopy cover is another lever
that cities can use to be able to combat heat.
And so we provide at the census level data
so that cities can understand
and predict what will actually happen
if they pass policies as well.
So that is where I'll leave you,
but happy, this is just a smattering of our solutions.
You can see there's a lot that AI can do quickly
both on the protecting our Earth
and on the resilience side,
and happy to dive into much more as we get further.
- Thank you so much. That's really exciting.
And we'll talk more
about some of those resources that you shared.
Do you wanna go ahead and switch?
Okay, thank you.
So I'll introduce our second panelist now.
Dr. Gaurav Khanna is an AI executive at Cisco Systems.
During his 25 year career at Cisco,
he's had many roles
including managing early-in-career SE programs
and founding the first data science
and machine learning team in sales.
His team pioneered the use
of predictive and generative AI systems and sales at Cisco.
In his current role, he's focused on guiding customers
and their overall AI strategy and business transformation.
He's also active fostering strategic partnerships
with Cisco and the industry.
Teaching and mentoring students have long been a passion.
He currently teaches a popular foundational AI ML course
at Stanford Continuing Studies
and travels frequently to speak about AI
and industry forums.
Originally from New York, he's been a long-time resident
of San Jose.
And I will go ahead and,
let's see, hopefully.
- [Gaurav] If if it doesn't come up, I can.
- Okay.
- Well, I'll go ahead and ask you your first question then,
and we'll hope for the best
- [Gaurav] Okay. All right. - with that.
How significant is the problem shortfall
of the energy needed to power AI systems?
Is this something we can overcome?
What are the consequences of not being able
to meet these power needs?
- Okay, I think we'll just wing it.
Excellent question, Julie,
that's just amazing work that your team's doing.
I wanna build on that a little bit.
So, I don't know if some of you saw
the opening panel this morning with Karen Howe,
that was very powerful.
So let me build on that a little bit.
So the thing that we're talking about when we talk about AI
that is the power equation
in all of this are these things called data centers.
I don't know if you've seen any of 'em.
It's not like a place you hang out and, like, have a beer.
These are, like, the most boring places you'll go.
And, you know, I've worked in them a lot of my life,
and it's just banks and banks and banks
and racks of servers.
And it wasn't a big deal.
They're around, I think there are a couple,
you know, in this area here,
so you don't even notice them as you drive by them.
So there were these unassuming warehouses
of these servers that powered Google,
it powered Facebook,
it powered all the different services
that you use online.
What has happened is these have gone into overdrive with AI,
and they are the ones
that increasingly they are putting a tax on the grid,
and the projections are that by the next five years,
they will consume about 13%
of all the power in this country.
I mean, just think about that.
13% of all the power in this country
to just power these data centers.
There's data out there that predicts
that the largest hyperscalers,
now, these are the big companies,
Google, Meta, Oracle, Microsoft,
the largest hyperscalers will consume
as much power as the country of Portugal.
(chuckles) I mean, you know, if you've been to Portugal,
you know this is not a country in standstill.
It's a dynamic country.
People use power,
and just these companies are using as much as a country.
So that's what we're getting to.
So why is this happening?
And I want to get to the consequence,
Carla, that you mentioned, 'cause that's important.
So the culprits are these things called GPUs,
graphic processing units.
And they had sort of an unassuming birth, right?
They were meant to accelerate video and graphics.
So, you know, when I was growing up,
the cool kids had a GPU in their PC
and they would be able to play video games.
As it turns out,
AI requires some very specialized math processing.
And the same math that was required to accelerate,
you know, the shoot 'em up games in video games
actually happened to be the same math
that powers autonomous vehicles,
Bitcoin mining, and AI.
So NVIDIA is, like, the luckiest company on earth
because (chuckles) they built this thing
for video processing,
and now all of a sudden they're in the middle
of this AI revolution.
GPUs were never designed,
now, I'm gonna channel my inner Karen Howe,
they were never designed to be energy efficient.
Never. Because why?
Right, they lived in these unassuming data centers.
They lived in scientific research facilities
that did scientific modeling.
So they were contained and yes, they used a lot of power,
but they just weren't that many of 'em
relatively speaking for most of history.
And so there was really no incentive to make them cool.
So they burned hot and they burned hotter and hotter.
And when AI came about,
so this is, I'm talking about 10 years ago,
before ChatGPT, GPUs were found,
as I mentioned, to accelerate the math for machine learning,
what we used to call machine learning,
and when Gen AI came out,
not only did that spread like wildfire
across the world, as we know,
but the math required for GPT
was even greater than anything we've seen.
So just for reference, a ChatGPT query,
so when you go into ChatGPT
and you put in a prompt,
that is 10x the energy
it takes for a Google search, okay?
And now, you already know that you're getting more
out of that than, you know,
this is nothing against Google,
but GPT search is a lot more information
that you're getting certainly than sometimes a set of links.
Either way, that energy required to generate that text
that you see in front of you is that much greater.
So these GPUs are really the culprit here,
and they're not getting any cooler.
And if you have an industry that is just taking off
and everybody needs these GPUs,
you can't say, "Well, time out.
Stop. Everybody hold up.
Let me make these cooler
and then you'll get 'em next year."
No, it's like, "I need 'em now."
And that's part of my job is to talk to customers,
and every day we're talking about how many GPUs they need,
and I'm painfully aware
that what they need to build to run these GPUs
and the energy they need is gargantuan.
So let me share kind of where we're going.
I mentioned that these data centers
are gonna take all this energy.
Here's where we're at.
It is predicted
that we will need 56 gigawatts of energy
by the end of this decade to power all of this AI.
When you look at what is being built,
so the extra energy that's coming onto the grid,
and you look at what is,
if you look at what's already coming on the grid
and the extra capacity that is in our grid,
we are still gonna be short 36 gigawatts of power
by the end of this decade.
Now, when you hear, you know,
this gigawatt, that gigawatt, 10 gigawatt,
you might be like, you know,
Dr. Emmett Brown in "Back to the Future."
"1.21 gigawatts, oh my God,
how could I have been so stupid?"
Okay, so 36-gigawatt shortfall
is enough to power 1/5
of the households in the United States,
or all the homes in Texas and California combined.
Recent studies have shown
that that's off by a factor of two.
We're actually (chuckles) gonna be short 70 gigawatts.
So the consequence, Carla, sorry,
finally getting to your question,
the consequence is a few things.
One is that it puts a break on the whole system,
and in fact I've talked to,
I have the privilege of talking
to a lot of different people about AI,
and I've learned an immense amount in the past few years.
Power is a huge problem,
and it actually is putting the brakes on projects.
I've met some partners of ours that are literally,
they have equipment in their lab that they can't power up
because the local utility has not been able to dig a trench
to get power to their lab.
So it's putting the brakes on things, number one.
Number two, which I think is interesting
just from a technical point of view,
is it's revived the whole concept of nuclear power.
Now, we're immigrants to the United States,
very proud immigrants, moved here in 1982 to New York,
and, you know, the memory of Three Mile Island
was very fresh at that time.
It wasn't anywhere near where we lived,
but, like, people talked about it.
Like, I remember in fifth grade, you know,
my teacher talking about Three Mile Island,
and I was just beside myself that they're restarting
one of the reactors of Three Mile Island
(chuckles) to power a Microsoft data center.
I was like, "What are we gonna spin up next? Chernobyl?
I mean, come on. Like, why stop there?"
So, but in all seriousness,
the nuclear power that they're thinking about today,
I'm not here to advocate for it,
I'm just talking about a solution
that is potentially possible,
are very small modular nuclear reactors.
They're about the size of the lot of your home,
and they run locally and they can power these data centers.
Interestingly enough, they actually have
some bipartisan support,
because as Karen Howe was talking about today,
and it may be obvious
from some of the reporting you've seen,
what we don't want is a situation like Memphis,
which is incredibly sad.
I dunno if you've seen the reporting,
but basically Grok came in there
and there's 30,
I mean, she said 35,
I thought it was (chuckles) more.
Ether way, these things are just spewing
this just noxious gas into the community.
(chuckles) And the city leaders are like,
"Well, we didn't know."
So, you know, they were duped.
We don't want that for every data center.
So in a way, I think part of the reason
these nuclear reactors, these small nuclear reactors,
are getting all this attention and bipartisan support
where they wouldn't is fundamentally,
they're not Chernobyl, they're not Three Mile Island.
It's a completely different world today.
You can design these reactors.
But it's a way to provide
that 36-gigawatt shortfall
without pumping noxious fumes into the air, right?
There's very few technologies
that can actually make up for the shortfall.
So it's bringing into conversation
technologies that we've forgotten about,
but it's bringing it up
because actually, a lot of people don't want a consequence
where we're generating this great AI
but we're causing all this environmental harm.
I mean, Juliet presented some amazing examples
how AI can be used to make small changes, big changes
to help the environment.
Well, this is one way to do it, right?
Nuclear power is actually able to provide
that much energy to power
these power-hungry GPUs
without spewing noxious fumes into the air, right?
There are other consequences, but this is one option.
But on a more philosophical level,
now I'm speaking as Gaurav Khanna, not as a Cisco employee,
what I think will happen is that people will pause, okay?
If you cannot get enough power,
'cause the utility cannot dig a trench
to lay the power line down to power your AI,
you have to stop and think, "What am I doing this for?
What am I building? Do I need this much power?
Do I need this much AI?"
And if you think about it,
that's a very fundamentally different approach
than we took when the internet launched
and when the cloud computing became big,
it's like, oh, great, internet,
boom, everybody, (chuckles) use the internet browser.
You know, it boomed, the sale of PCs boomed
in the wake of the internet,
and cloud computing,
the data centers and the data center footprint
boomed without really any consequence
in thinking about maybe,
you know, what's this gonna mean?
Like, people just built it out.
We wanted more salesforce.com, we wanted more Google,
we wanted more Meta.
With AI, I feel very early on in the cycle,
the fact that we're short on power
will make people pause and think,
"What on earth are we doing here,
and how can we build this properly?"
And Jory said something really great this morning
about being intentional about equity
in the process of thinking about education by design.
I actually just saw him outside, by design.
He said that and I told him I'd work it in.
So if you see Jory, tell him I worked it in,
because you have to think
about the environmental consequences
by design from the beginning,
not some afterthought later
after, you know, half the things
that you care about are destroyed.
And so I think giving people a moment to pause and reflect
and think about how we do this intentionally by design
is probably gonna be one of the greatest legacies
of this power shortfall.
And I'm starting to see it now,
because people are putting things on hold,
and when you put things on hold,
you have a time to stop and reflect.
So I think those are the three consequences.
Yeah.
- Okay.
I will pose the next question to Juliet.
So you talked a lot about how Google
is responding to environmental impacts
and helping to mitigate things like flooding and fires.
Can you talk a little bit about AI solutions
and scaling AI solutions
that can help with climate,
help to reduce the climate impacts of AI?
- Yeah.
Thank you Carla,
and Gaurav, it was great to hear
your remarks and your talks.
Yes, energy use is a very important component of AI.
Absolutely.
And yeah, it's something we think a lot about.
Maybe just starting there
and then I'll get into solutions.
One of the pieces that Google released recently
was an analysis
not only of the efficiency of GPUs,
those chips that Gaurav was talking about,
but also the efficiency of an overall query, right?
Of, you know,
I'm gonna ask Google's Gemini some question.
How much energy does that take?
And what we found is,
because we take a full-stack approach
to how we work with AI,
we actually have our own type of chips also called TPUs.
We use some NVIDIA chips
and some chips from other sources as well.
And what we found was that we were able
to actually reduce the energy required
for a query over 12 months by a factor of 33.
And so, you know,
instead of using 33x energy, we're using one.
And so really significant improvements in efficiency
in part driven because out of necessity, right,
you know, there are very real constraints
in terms of what's actually possible,
and in part from Google's strong environmental commitments
and in a variety of different forms.
So I think we're gonna see a lot
of different movement on a lot of different parts
of the stack as time goes on.
But going to, you know,
what are really the solutions that we can have,
so in the first part of my remarks
where I talked about transportation and energy solutions,
all of those solutions are helping mitigate climate change.
If you read Google's 2024 Environmental Report,
what you'll notice is that Google's 2024 CO2 emissions
were 11.5 megatons.
And if you look at just five of our AI solutions,
things like the Solar API that I talked about,
things like that green leaf fuel efficient routing
in Google maps,
they saved in 2024
26 megatons of CO2 equivalent.
And so we're already seeing the AI solutions
from a climate standpoint
outweigh the emissions of Google overall,
not just Google's, you know, AI use,
but that includes things
like my plane flight to New York earlier this week,
for example, in that prior calculus.
And so I think when we take a step back,
yes, AI energy is an important thing to be talking about.
We should also be talking about EVs and energy
by the way as well, right?
Because we've seen a tremendous electrification of vehicles
that really is affecting the energy needs on our grid also,
which is a great thing from a climate standpoint,
but also gonna mean that we need
to start building more flexibility into the grid,
building more modernization into the grid
in a way that we haven't had in the past.
If you look at other countries around the world,
their grids respond much faster, they're much more flexible.
We've seen very little load growth over the U.S.
in the past number of years.
And I think AI is really gonna push us
both towards climate solutions
and also towards more of the energy solutions
that we're gonna need to see.
- Yeah, one of the things I really appreciate
about what you presented
was that some of these changes are very small,
like, what you can do at a traffic light
or having the pilots change their flight.
They're small at an individual level,
but in aggregate, they make a huge change.
A long time,
now, I'm gonna get a little bit nostalgic,
one of the first articles I wrote for my school newspaper
in high school, this will date myself,
was there was a book that came out
in Earth Day, I think 1989,
and it was called "50 Things You Can Do
to Save the Planet."
And it was all, like, little things,
like recycle this and recycle that.
And the point of the book was,
if we all do these things, it'll be better.
So a couple of examples thinking about it
is about small changes.
You actually don't need the full power of GPT
for every query.
And one of my sort of conversations with customers,
'cause then we start to get into design, is,
what language models do you actually need?
And a lot of times it's not the large ones.
Sometimes you use the large ones,
but a lot of times they're much smaller purpose models
that actually can now run on your laptop
that can do the tasks that you need.
So just for context,
just a little bit of language model science
and then we can get back to the environment.
So, ChatGPT, Gemini, Llama,
you pick it, they're trained on, like,
the world's data, right?
So if you think about it,
just as an analogy, to train GPT,
you need all of the world's books.
But to fine-tune a model
to be very specific to what you want to do,
so for example, you're Southwest Airlines
and you want your chatbot to sound like Southwest Airlines,
and they always make fun
of airline safety regulations, right?
Or you're Disney and you want to make a Disney chatbot,
you want it to sound like Mickey Mouse.
The amount of data it takes to do that is one bookshelf.
So you use the entire world's books
to train the model to speak English
and you use a bookshelf to train it
to speak like Mickey Mouse.
So these large language models are huge,
and they can do everything
because they have been tuned to do everything
or trained to do everything.
They can tell you about history,
they can tell you about the French Revolution,
they can talk like a pirate, they can do all of that.
But as a company, you don't need all of that.
So what people have started to do was to take models,
smaller models, they're not as big,
and then fine-tune them using a bookshelf's worth of data
for something very specific.
And that is very, very, very power efficient.
And so if we become just, I mean,
this sort of parallels small changes you can make,
if you can start to change that in your company
where you allow your employees to use systems
that just inherently use less power with every search,
you start to build a basis of just more efficient use,
so you're not needing the full power
of GPT all the time, number one.
Number two, just to add to the power equation,
one of the things that I think is gonna be really important
is that we're starting to cool these systems
with water, with different types of fluids
that can actually reduce the overall energy impact.
But as Karen mentioned, which is really important,
and I don't want to, you know, minimize the impact of this,
is you need clean water.
So we have to think, again, really deliberately,
do we want to build this in the desert southwest,
(chuckling) which is already suffering
from lower levels of water in the Colorado River.
So you have to be really mindful of what you're doing
to cool these things.
But again, it goes back to,
I'm seeing these things happen now, not as an afterthought,
because these things are becoming breaks on the system,
which I think, you know, as a technologist,
it's sometimes hard to say this, you know,
you wanna say "Go, go, go,"
but I think it's important and healthy as a society
to have these kinds of breaks,
and power and energy is acting as a significant break
to make people really think
- So, Gaurav, you touched on something
as you were talking about the energy usage
between ChatGPT or just a regular Google search,
and most of the folks in the room are educators,
and so one of the things that I've observed
in working with students
is that they tend to be very binary
in their thoughts and feelings on AI.
So there's the camp that think AI is bad,
it's bad for the environment, we shouldn't use it,
and then there's the camp that thinks it's awesome
'cause it'll write my English paper for me.
And there's not a lot of in between.
And so my question for both of you is,
what would you recommend,
how can the folks in the room
share with students
on how to responsibly use AI
from kind of an energy consumption perspective?
- I have a thought on that, if I can kick this off.
So as part of our paper
that we released recently,
we really wanted to bring numbers to this problem, right?
So actually, my mom has taught in shared accounting
at a community college
for the past 20 years, that has been her role,
and so she's always trained me to think in numbers.
And the truth is actually that climate change
is a numbers problem.
It is an accounting problem, right?
It is where are our greenhouse gases coming from?
How much are they? What are the sources?
If we take a look at those actions we can take,
what actually matters?
So as my team looks across all of our solutions for climate
that you were asking about, Carla,
we look to say, "Great, if we take each of these actions,
how big is each of these actions?
How many people can we get to take it?
And let's run out the forecast
for how big this solution can be."
We live in numbers.
Now, a number that I think is really important
for people to be aware of
came out of our recent paper recently
around the energy consumption.
And I was just looking it up, actually,
while Gaurav, you were speaking,
because I wanted to make sure that I got the number right.
So take watching TV, for example.
I'd love some numbers from the audience,
how long watching TV do you think the median query on Gemini
is from an energy equivalency standpoint?
Does anybody have any guess?
How long would you have to watch TV to use the same amount
of energy as-
- [Audience Member] Five minutes.
- Five minutes? Anybody else?
- An hour. - A week.
- A week, an hour?
The answer is nine seconds.
Yeah, and so this is why I think
when we talk about responsibly using AI,
maybe you should turn off TV
during the commercials instead
and ask a few AI queries, right?
So I think we really need to,
this is why numbers are so important
because they really affect the driving
of what we do.
I use AI at work all the time.
It makes me far more efficient.
My job is around making us more sustainable.
And so, you know, I use it continually.
Yesterday I was playing around vibe-coding an app
to recommend irrigation
that was water conserving for our orchard.
And there's a lot that you can do using AI
that can be towards sustainable actions.
And so I think it really is, you know,
both I encourage students to understand AI
so that they can understand its potential.
Just earlier this week, Google released AI Quests,
which are geared,
granted, I think the target is younger students
than for community college,
more around kind of middle school, high school,
but allowing them to play around
and simulate using AI
to predict floods, just like our flood forecasting solution
that I was presenting earlier.
I think, you know, if students are not understanding
how to use AI as a part of their day to day,
they're not gonna be as efficient
or as productive as they otherwise could be.
And with that, I think it's important to understand,
hopefully they'll do something
that will save more than nine seconds of TV
with each of the queries that they generate.
- That's excellent.
And in fact, I wanna build on that point.
I don't know that students can necessarily, you know,
because I am the parent of two teenagers,
they need something, they just go to ChatGPT,
I'm not gonna tell 'em, "Well,
think about what you're gonna use."
They're like, "I gotta get this done, I gotta ask ChatGPT."
So I don't know if that that's the right avenue,
but to build on what Juliet said, I think it's important
'cause remember, we already have the agency
to choose the companies we want to buy products from
based on their impact on the environment,
their corporate social governance, all of that,
we have, as consumers and investors, that choice.
And I know ESG might be a bad term these days.
I think it's actually wonderful.
So you actually should work with companies
and use the products from them
that are thinking about this, right?
I mean, Google has been on this, Juliet,
as your work has illustrated for a long time.
I mean, I'll speak for my company Cisco.
This is a big part of the ethos of our company
in terms of just design, right?
The power efficiency cooling
and the impact on the environment
from the entire supply chain, how we refurbish products,
all of that goes into a score that our company gets
for how environmentally sustainable our practices are.
So, you know, think about that,
because actually now, you'll have a choice.
One of the great things that I think is happening,
and we touched on it earlier, is you actually have a choice
now of which language model to use, right?
ChatGPT was kind of there for a long time.
It had the lead.
I think that there are wonderful language models out there,
and you have a lot of choice,
and you can pick the companies
that are thinking about how to do this responsibly.
I think as a student, that's something
you can incorporate
not just for AI but just everything
that you have as a consumer,
because that's the agency that you have.
- That's great. Thank you.
We have about 13 minutes left,
and so I wanted to open it up to the audience
and see if you all have any pressing questions
that you would like to ask of our panelists.
Yes.
- [Audience Member] Yeah, I think it's kind of
for both of you,
you both touched upon the energy usage
and that nine seconds, I kind of looked it up,
it seems like about 0.5 watt hours is what a query uses.
Do you feel that as the chills get faster
or get more energy efficient like the NVIDIA Blackwell
and the algorithmic changes, I mean,
is that gonna be increasingly going down per use
for query usage,
and did the extra 36 gigawatts required
to take that into account?
Or did they assume the current usage for query?
- I think the studies show
sort of, you know, what could happen.
So, you ask a really good question.
So the chips are gonna get more efficient,
but the utilization
of those GPUs is already skyrocketing, for two reasons.
One is the use of AI and our use of AI is spreading.
I asked a question this morning,
how many people had already used GPT today,
and a few hands went up.
So that just tells you, (chuckles) you know,
you wake up in the, I don't know,
I hope you had some coffee before you used it.
It wasn't, like, (Juliet chuckles)
the first thing you did when you got out of bed.
But I'm that way too.
I mean, it just sort of starts the morning,
you know, in the morning when I use it.
So the utilization skyrocketing
because our own use of it in our lives
is incorporated, is increasing.
The second thing, and I won't go into details
'cause it's a bit wonky, but there's this term,
you may have heard of it, called agentic AI,
and agentic AI basically is transforming AI
from being able to do queries,
you know, Q&A, like what we do, to actually executing tasks.
And what that means is you actually set up a system
of language models
or language models and their minions to go execute tasks.
And so now, the machines are talking to each other,
and that's generating what we call tokens.
That's sort of the atomic unit
of what these language models consume and output.
So this token utilization is growing,
this is a group of educators,
so I can use a little bit of math, right?
So the power utilization
is becoming more efficient by x squared,
but the use is growing by e to the x,
and for those of you who ever took math,
e to the x always wins.
So (chuckles) that's unfortunately what's happening,
is that, I think that 36-gigawatt shortfall
is actually an underestimate, as I mentioned,
taking into account everything that you mentioned,
- I haven't looked into those numbers specifically.
So yeah, we wouldn't be able to comment on that.
I do think that, you know,
I do expect that overall energy use from AI
will increase even with the efficiency gains that we see
because of increased utilization,
which is in part also, I think, you know,
I think we need to solve this energy problem, right?
It's absolutely critical that we solve it.
We wanna solve it in a sustainable way.
Google has committed to 24/7 carbon-free electricity.
So Google was the first major purchaser
to offset all of our electricity purchases
with renewable energy.
This was maybe 15 years ago or so.
And now, Google has set the bar even higher,
which is to match on an hour-by-hour basis
with renewables consumption.
So that means even when the sun isn't shining, for example,
let's make sure we get our electricity from renewables,
and it's important that we solve that problem, right?
And that's not gonna be an easy problem.
It's gonna be something that's gonna require
a lot of focus and a lot of work.
But I also think there's another side to it too.
And, you know, we've just talked about the use cases
in energy and climate, right?
But there are a whole variety of additional use cases
for ways that AI can increase our productivity
overall as a society.
And so I think there's that other lens,
and, you know, the fact that AI usage is increasing
is a testament to that.
And how do we make sure that we can do that
in a sustainable way?
- [Audience Member] I'm just gonna make a comment.
I agree that the AI usage is going up,
but I thought it was an interesting observation,
you said that you choose to use GPT
when in fact it's the,
I'm in the process of teaching AI literacy to students
and my other faculty, which (indistinct) way behind, right,
the technology now, and when they open their email,
they're using, they may not know,
but a lot of these things are turned on by default,
so they're using AI and they're not even choosing to use AI.
- And that's a good point,
and I think what you're hinting at
is there's some measure of a lack of control.
You know, like for example, if you work in an organization
that has some kind of copilot,
and I'm not referring to a Microsoft Copilot,
I'm talking about copilot-type systems
that were, you know, built by a company
that's not as sort of, you know,
as thoughtful about AI, then yeah, you're sort of stuck
because you have to use that system in your company.
I guess where I was going at is
in the parts of your life
where you have the agency to choose,
you can choose to otherwise use things, you know,
from companies that are mindful of these things.
But I do understand that there's a level of,
well, you know, it just came with the system
that I bought, and that's what there is to it.
And I suspect there'll be some of that too.
What I will say, so,
my observation is, just for context,
I work with a lot of customers
that Cisco has west of the Mississippi,
and these are sort of anywhere companies from 500
to let's say 15,000, 20,000 employees.
And I can tell you uniformly,
what's really heartening
is that there's a lot of thought about exactly this.
I mean, yes, some people are not necessarily driven
by altruistic means,
they're just literally looking at the bottom line
is how much power this is gonna cost me.
But, you know, I keep coming back to this point.
It's bringing up all of these other issues
that we've been talking about,
about what really matters here,
what do we need to deploy,
what do we need to give our employees,
and where should it come from?
And there's actually something else
that's not exactly related to the environment,
but Karen brought it up this morning,
which is really important,
which is, besides being a good company
and being a steward of the environment,
you have to make sure you produce AI that's safe,
'cause she was talking about how these language models
can actually output incredibly biased
and toxic and harmful content.
I mean, you have to see, I hope nobody's seen this,
but if you've seen it, I mean,
it rattles you
even if you're a data scientist and you know it's coming
and it's just, she was talking about that group in Kenya
and I was almost in tears
because I, when I read about that I was like,
"Wow, what do we do to these people?"
And so part of,
it's not directly related to climate,
but part of what companies are thinking about,
just to give you an example
of how different the conversation is this time,
they're very mindful that, you know,
I don't wanna buy a chatbot from a company
that doesn't care about the output.
Like, what safeguards did they put in?
So I'm very heartened
that issues that were absent
during the internet era and the cloud era,
we just didn't ask these kind of ethical questions.
They're, like, right in front of us.
You know, I didn't know
that taking on this job I'd become,
like, part-time ethicist.
But I'm glad it's happening
because, you know, we want this world,
we want a responsible AI world.
- Yeah, well said.
Thank you.
Cameron?
- Yeah.
- [Cameron] So, that is a perfect segue
for my question.
So, so far today, we've talked a lot
about individual practices,
things we can do as an individual
that in the collective add up to a lot, that's to be sure.
And I love the sense of agency you've given me here,
but I also wonder about the role of policymaking
and policymakers to catalyze that impact.
What sort of guardrails should our policymakers
be making now, putting in place now,
to spearhead, to accelerate these sort of offsets
that are needed?
At the same time, I recognize that it's a fine line
because we don't want to impede technological advancement.
We want to move fast and break things.
I get that need.
We don't want to fall behind
and become less nationally competitive in the AI race.
But I also would like to hear from you,
what do you feel is the role for policymaking
to move us beyond,
"Cameron is a good AI actor
'cause he turns off ChatGPT-5
from his full capacity
and dials it down to,
we are a collective, you know,
actors of, you know, AI doing well
because of policy put in place"?
- I'll answer from a more limited perspective
because I don't work on AI policy,
even though it's a fascinating area
and one obviously that is critically important.
And I'll answer from an energy use standpoint,
and then I'm interested, Gaurav,
to hear your broader point.
But really there is so much policy that is needed
to facilitate shifting our grid more rapidly, right?
I mean, if you look at how difficult it is
to build new transmission infrastructure for our grid,
it's extraordinarily challenging.
If you look at the last time
that the U.S. built a new nuclear plant
and you compare that with the last time
that China built a new nuclear plant,
we have a lot of catching up to do
from an energy grid perspective,
and so things that we can do to facilitate
more power getting added to the grid
in a clean and a sustainable way
are gonna be really helpful from an energy point of view.
But your question was broader than that,
so I'll hand it to Gaurav.
- Please allow me to get riled up for two seconds,
and then I'll calm down. (audience chuckles)
So this Memphis example I think will become
business school case studies for a long time,
because what Karen said is that was a mixed community
in that section of Memphis,
I think it's East Memphis, that is now suffering.
They already had health issues,
they were suffering from the noxious fumes
from these methane turbines.
What she didn't mention, but she knows,
is that the city council is made up
of people from that community.
It's a mixed ethnic group of people.
I mean, this was a complete fail.
They failed to protect their peeps, right?
I mean, that to me is so mind-boggling.
And what she said is apparent
is that they did not bring in people in the community
or any experts to ask them.
My intern could have told them
that if they're building (chuckles)
100,000 GPU system, it's gonna need power.
Where is it gonna come from?
Any intern who's studying data science
could have told you that.
So one nice thing
is that I do see local governments, state governments,
I've actually testified in front of a few of 'em
just to give them sort of expert opinion,
that's how you do things, you know,
she was saying that, like,
collect information from people in the community.
Policymaking is best when you get a diverse set
of opinions from experts.
And we generally tend to do that.
It's very apparent when we fail and don't do that.
So the role of policymaking,
I can't say this policy versus that,
the role of good governance is to seek expertise
'cause you as a lawmaker are not an expert
in GPUs and GPU power,
but there are plenty of people who are
that are probably in your district,
so bring them in to get your opinion.
And I think that you're gonna find
a remarkable amount of consensus.
Frankly, you know, like I said, I cover red states,
I cover blue states, (chuckles)
and I don't see anybody saying,
"Yeah, let's spew more power
and pollution into the environment."
Nobody's saying that,
but we have to now start getting more nuance,
and policymaking is taking these abstract concepts
that we all believe in
and turning it into the nuts and bolts and text of policy.
And that's expert opinion.
That is what government officials should do.
And if you're not doing that, you are failing your people.
So, okay.
I'll step off my soapbox.
- I think more people should ask him questions
and get him on his soapbox. (audience chuckles)
- [Audience Member] Following up on that,
kind of the elephant in the room, literally,
is the federal government policy
and, you know, one of the few industries I think
that has the collective power to try and fight back
against the idiocy of the energy policy
is the tech industry.
And I know that this probably above pay grade,
(indistinct) your scope of work,
but does anybody ever talk about,
you know, the tech industry knowing
of these energy needs, getting together and say,
"Well, the fastest way to get new energy
is renewable energy,
and why don't we all form a collective
and advocate for that?"
- One thing I can say is that Google
is a part of the Clean Energy Buyers Alliance
that is very much geared along the lines
of what you're suggesting,
of advocating for clean energy.
- Yeah, the challenge is they are doing that.
The problem is it takes longer
to bring those online than it does
to just burn what we've done for, you know, generations,
which is burn.
So I think that's part of the problem,
is this whole thing that we needed fast and we did now,
and this data center has to go up because,
so, let me back up.
Part of what's driving a massive investment
in all these data centers
is that there's this feeling,
unlike other technology inflection points,
there's a feeling that if we don't make this investment,
it's an existential threat.
I don't know another time in our history
where companies that have market valuations over a trillion
feel like they're gonna vanish overnight.
I mean, it's just mind-boggling to me
that, (chuckles) like, they feel that way.
But I feel that that is what's driving
some of the conversation, that we need to build this now.
And when you need to build it now,
you are short-circuiting
what you may believe in your heart
that we need to do it this right way,
because it's very hard to get renewable energy,
even though it's the right thing to do.
It's very hard to bring that online.
It's very hard to bring,
well, it varies by state,
but in some states, it's hard to bring online.
There's a lot of permitting,
there's a lot of regulations you have to go through.
And in other states, it's not.
So it's just a mixed bag across the country.
The thing is, there isn't enough renewable capacity
that was already waiting there to be used by data centers,
and that was the problem.
If we had built out a generation earlier
all of this renewable sources,
we may not have been in the situation we're in now,
but unfortunately, we started a little bit late,
and like you said, policies change,
or at least as you hinted,
policies change administration to administration.
Part of the reason I mention nuclear power
is because it's not necessarily renewable
in the same sense, right?
You have to dig up the fuel for it.
But it is able to do it
and provide that capacity without polluting.
And really, if you think about it,
you won't be able to build solar grids
and wind farms fast enough for 36 gigawatts,
which is why nuclear sort of emerged
as one of the only solutions
that you can do in a sustainable way.
Otherwise, you would just have to build
more methane turbines,
which, you know, I don't want, certainly,
I don't think anybody here wants either.
- Well, we are technically out of time.
I had so many more questions that I wanted to ask,
and I'm sure you all did too,
and so I wanna thank both of our panelists.
I think this aws a really great conversation,
and I'm hopeful that we can continue it.
I will give you a chance to thank them in just one second,
but I'm gonna put in a plug
because we have our climate conference, C3 Converge,
which is the California Community College Climate Summit
that will be happening in Anaheim in two weeks,
September 29th and 30th.
And so these conversations will continue there
on the AI side of the house.
So please, if you're able to, please join us for that.
And now, please join me
in thanking our two panelists for being here.
(audience applauds)
And thank you all for being here also.
- Yeah, likewise. I appreciated your remarks.
We have a lot of work.